<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An outragious out--cry for tithes, and a deep charge of stealing, cheating, robbing, &amp;c. for not paying of them (contained in nine reasons, sent some few daies since in print to divers) answered.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90218</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863151</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115335</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240946421</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing O599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E678_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203063</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863151</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99863151e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115335)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 104:E678[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An outragious out--cry for tithes, and a deep charge of stealing, cheating, robbing, &amp;c. for not paying of them (contained in nine reasons, sent some few daies since in print to divers) answered.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills, and are to be sold at his house in Fleet-yard next door to the Rose and Crown, and by William Larnar at the Blackmoor at Fleet-Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLII. [1652]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: The dreadfull danger of sacriledge in the with-holding of tithes.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob. 24.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Nalson, James, 1600-1662, --  attributed name.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Dreadfull danger of sacriledge in the with-holding of tithes.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115335:1"/>
            <p>AN <hi>OƲTRAGIOƲS OƲT-CRY</hi> FOR TITHES, AND A DEEP CHARGE OF Stealing, Cheating, Robbing, &amp;c. for not paying of them (Contained in nine Reasons, sent some few daies since in Print to divers) ANSWERED.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSLAM 119.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I am a stranger in Earth: hide not thy Commandments from me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> and are to be sold at his house in <hi>Fleet-yard</hi> next door to the <hi>Rose and Crown,</hi> and by <hi>William Larnar</hi> at the <hi>Blackmoor</hi> at <hi>Fleet-Bridge</hi> MDCLII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115335:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115335:2"/>
            <head>To the Christian or but Civil Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courtious Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Eeting with a dreadfull <hi>Out-cry</hi> after <hi>Thieves, Cheaters, Robbers,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">The occasion of this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.</note> I list<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and asked if the cry were just, or the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties charged innocent: for, I remembred that in this famous City, <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Cheaters</hi> have been known to cry out <hi>Thievs</hi> and <hi>Cheaters</hi> first.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nine Reasons</hi> (some few daies since) are sent in <hi>Print</hi> by a noted Person,
<note place="margin">The Business of Tithes but a matter of money:</note> unto divers (not free for <hi>Tiths</hi>) I perceive the <hi>Author</hi> of them is serious and pretends the <hi>Statutes</hi> both of <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Heaven,</hi> and therefore with a <hi>soft,</hi> yet <hi>serious</hi> hand have I turn'd over the leaves of both.</p>
            <p>Truly if it were but a matter of <hi>Money</hi> (which yet is all the <hi>Matter</hi> of this worlds <hi>Cumbustions</hi>) why should we the mad Sons of men, spend this <hi>inestimable Minute</hi> of our short <hi>passage</hi> (as or'e the <hi>Thames,</hi> &amp;c.) from the shore of <hi>Time,</hi> to the other side of <hi>Eternity,</hi> in <hi>drowning</hi> and <hi>damning</hi> each other for a <hi>dry Crust,</hi> which is all that this worlds <hi>boat</hi> can give us?</p>
            <p>No, saith this <hi>Author,</hi> this business of <hi>Tithes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Yet preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the cause of Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus &amp;c.</note> is the cause of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> of his <hi>Gospel,</hi> of his <hi>Ministry,</hi> and of the <hi>Souls</hi> of men and of their <hi>Salvations</hi> or <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> on the other side.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115335:3"/>
            <p>I yeild it, and say with <hi>Isaiah,</hi> let us shew our selves men, and in a <hi>humane, civil,</hi> and <hi>Christian</hi> way debate it. we that name the name of <hi>Christ,</hi> are agreed upon the <hi>Test</hi> and <hi>Touch-stone</hi> of this, pretended, <hi>coin</hi> and <hi>metal.</hi> Surely, we are both like to say as that renowned <hi>Cromwel</hi> in <hi>H. 8.</hi> his dayes, and from his person <hi>Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> to an Assembly of <hi>Bishops</hi> met about <hi>Religion:</hi> The <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> (I am sure of it) resolves to have all tried by Scripture. But</p>
            <p>Who shall judge of the Scriptures <hi>sense, Intepretation, Application,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
            <p>I answer,
<note place="margin">The Judge in Controversies of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship.</note> in <hi>Civil Matters, Custom, Tribute,</hi> &amp;c. (yet although he parted with his <hi>Civil Right,</hi> to avoid offence) <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> borrows money of a Fish to discharge it. We ought to <hi>pay,</hi> to <hi>love,</hi> to honour to obey and pray for, even a <hi>Roman Caesar.</hi> In matters of <hi>God,</hi> of his <hi>Christ,</hi> his <hi>Gospel,</hi> his <hi>Ministry,</hi> his <hi>Scriptures,</hi> our <hi>Soules</hi> and <hi>Eternity, Caesar</hi> himself cannot be <hi>Judge,</hi> &amp;c. Let every man be fully perswaded in his own heart, saith <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans.</hi> And we manifest our selves to every mans <hi>Conscience</hi> in the sight of <hi>God,</hi> saith <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> In <hi>all</hi> therefore, in the <hi>least</hi> of these matters, each soul must be his own <hi>Judge,</hi> each individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Soul</hi> must be a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the poorest <hi>Lazarus</hi> an Emperor.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Author</hi> of these Reasons say so too, I have hope, he will see cause to cease his <hi>Out-cry,</hi> or return the sober <hi>Reasons</hi> of his continuance of it, which if he please (with his name, subscribed) to do.</p>
            <p>He promiseth to return no other payment (with his <hi>Name</hi> also) who yet desires no <hi>name</hi> but what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="rebuttal">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115335:3"/>
            <head>A soft Answer to an outragious <hi>Out-cry,</hi> against <hi>Sacriledge, Theft, Robbery, Cheating,</hi> and an <hi>Ʋnpardonable</hi> sin, the not paying of <hi>Tithes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He first Reason, <hi>It is</hi> stealing (saith the <hi>Author</hi> of the nine reasons) <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the eight Commandement, and</hi> Rom. 13. <hi>Render to all their dues,</hi> Custom <hi>to whom</hi> Custom, <hi>&amp;c. And he adds, that</hi> Tithes <hi>are due to the</hi> Minister <hi>by the</hi> Law <hi>of the</hi> Land, <hi>and the</hi> Minister <hi>hath as legal a</hi> Right <hi>to the</hi> Rates <hi>set upon houses, as the</hi> Landlord <hi>hath to his</hi> Rent, <hi>and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that breaketh this</hi> hedge, <hi>a</hi> Serpent <hi>shall bite him,</hi> Eccles. 10.8.</p>
            <p>I answer, First, the <hi>Title</hi> chargeth with <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> or stealing of holy <hi>Things:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The right to Tithes touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> I expected some proof of that <hi>charge,</hi> and that at least we should have heard of the second Commandement, which concerns <hi>Gods worship,</hi> &amp;c. But it seems he fears that second Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement will fail him, and flies to the eight, and calls the not paying of <hi>Tithes</hi> the <hi>stealing</hi> of his <hi>Goods.</hi> I answer therefore,</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is a two-fold <hi>Right</hi> unto this worlds goods, The first <hi>Divine</hi> and holy;
<note place="margin">Right two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. Divine which is not here pleaded.</note> this is pleaded for by the many thousands and ten thousands of <hi>Clergy Men</hi> of all <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Religions</hi> in the world, as to Maintenance, Wages, Tithes, &amp;c. This was the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115335:4"/>Right of the <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> to <hi>Tithes</hi> in <hi>Canaan,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> (in mystical <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Kingdom of <hi>Christ</hi>) pleads the <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> of receiving <hi>Temporals,</hi> for <hi>Spirituals,</hi> although as a <hi>Pattern</hi> and <hi>Example</hi> to all <hi>Christs</hi> Servants, himself who laboured most in <hi>Christ's</hi> work never <hi>inforced,</hi> nor <hi>demanded,</hi> nor <hi>desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> a <hi>payment</hi> or <hi>gift,</hi> but either was <hi>supplied</hi> by the <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary</hi> and free gift of the Saints, or in their failing (through <hi>poverty</hi> or <hi>neglect</hi>) his own honest <hi>labours</hi> and <hi>endeavours</hi> made up the Breach, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The second Right is <hi>Humane.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Humane.</note> Which is,</p>
            <p>First, <hi>Natural,</hi> which all <hi>Gods</hi> Creatures have, as their <hi>Birth-right</hi> to the <hi>Elements</hi> in Common, &amp;c. Such is the Right of Inheritance, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The second,
<note place="margin">The tenths not due, by ony Natural or civil right.</note>
               <hi>Civil,</hi> by consent of <hi>Bargain, Gift,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But neither as the <hi>Clergy</hi> are born <hi>mankind</hi> have they any Right to the tenth of their <hi>Neighbours</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, no more than their neighbours have to theirs: Nor by each particular mans <hi>Consent</hi> (in their parish circuit) for where such a <hi>Consent</hi> passeth, I confess a kind of <hi>Humane Right</hi> and due from the <hi>People,</hi> so co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting to the <hi>Ministers</hi> or Servants attending on whatever <hi>Religion</hi> in the world.</p>
            <p>But where no such <hi>Consent</hi> passeth, where <hi>conscience</hi> to <hi>God dares</hi> not consent, dares not worship <hi>God</hi> so and so, <hi>dares</hi> not choose such and such <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Worship,</hi> and consequently <hi>dares</hi> not maintain them in &amp; for their <hi>Services;</hi> for any man now to cry out <hi>Thievs, Thieves, Cheaters, Robbers,</hi> &amp;c. what is it but to sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the nineth as well as to abuse the <hi>eighth</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, to give a <hi>false</hi> witness, and to act his part, whose name <hi>imports</hi> a <hi>False Accuser,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The two great sins of the world, <hi>Will-worship</hi> &amp; <hi>Oppression,</hi> have cost in the Nations of the world with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115335:4"/>this,
<note place="margin">The two Grand Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, Will-worship and Oppression, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablished in all Nations by Law.</note> millions of <hi>Treasures</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> by <hi>Gods</hi> three sore plagues▪ <hi>Sword, Famine,</hi> and <hi>Pestilence,</hi> in all which <hi>God</hi> is Righteous: For have not these two <hi>Grand Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities,</hi> both in this, and in all Nations of the world, been established by <hi>Law?</hi> (<hi>Psal.</hi> 82.) for (in all humble reverence to former and this present <hi>Parliament</hi>) I ask if it be not <hi>Iniquity</hi> by <hi>Law,</hi> to force upon this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, about ten thousand Ministers or Servants, who must be received into every respective <hi>Town</hi> or <hi>Parish,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Law for Tithes.</note> whether the people will or no, who will minister or serve them as they please; who will leave them, and depart to <hi>fatter</hi> livings when they can get them, and who yet will by the <hi>Sword</hi> force them to pay to them (as some have computed) the fifth of what the <hi>Land</hi> produceth. And I adde, for the complaining of this thorny <hi>hedge,</hi> how many thousands are bitten by that <hi>Old Serpent</hi> and enemy of mankind, as <hi>Theeves, Chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Robbers,</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
            <p>If the people of this Nation should say to their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentatives</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> as the people of <hi>Israel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The people cannot give, nor the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Power of inforcing a Religion, &amp;c.</note> once said to <hi>Aaron,</hi> make us <hi>Gods</hi> that may go before us, make us a <hi>Religion,</hi> make us a <hi>Worship,</hi> make us <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters,</hi> appoint their maintenance, &amp;c. Yet could not the <hi>Parliament</hi> answer to <hi>God</hi> the receiving of such a Power, nor the Framing and inforcing on the Nation a <hi>Religion Worship, Ministry, Maintenance,</hi> which they judge best, such an act being essentially against the very <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> their own <hi>civill office,</hi> and the very <hi>Consciences</hi> and <hi>Souls</hi> of men.</p>
            <p>With much more <hi>Justice</hi> (ten thousand fold) may the <hi>civill State</hi> in act (for it is meerly a <hi>civill</hi> thing) that each <hi>Town</hi> or <hi>Parish</hi> in this Nation shall,
<note place="margin">The case of inforcing of Tithes illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated.</note> whether they will or no, receive such or such a <hi>Shoomaker</hi> (or any other <hi>Trades-man</hi>) that this <hi>Town</hi> shall buy their shoes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115335:5"/>of him only their <hi>Parish Shoo-maker,</hi> that one <hi>last</hi> shall serve all the <hi>Feet</hi> in the <hi>Parish,</hi> that if they break the Law, cry out of <hi>Oppression</hi> and help themselves by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Shoo-Makers,</hi> and <hi>Lasts,</hi> yet shall they be forc't to pay the <hi>Parish Shoomaker</hi> notwithstanding: if this be not the <hi>Case</hi> (and were ten thousand times less evil if it were the Case) let heaven and <hi>Earth</hi> be Judges.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<note place="margin">Tithes cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative.</note> were not <hi>Tithes</hi> meer <hi>Ceremonies</hi> shado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing out the acknowledgement of <hi>Royalty</hi> in the true <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> (the true King of <hi>Righteousness</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi>) <hi>Christ Iesus?</hi> were they not <hi>Figures</hi> of Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God; who commanded them not to all the Nations of the World, but only in that typical Land of <hi>Canaan?</hi> which <hi>typicall</hi> and <hi>holy</hi> Land God owned as his own peculiar out of all the World, and gave it freely to that figurative people of <hi>Israel,</hi> choosing out one <hi>Tribe</hi> of 12 which one <hi>Tribe</hi> had no <hi>Inheritance</hi> in the Division of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> as the other 11 had.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Ioseph</hi> justly enacts a fifth for <hi>Pharaoh</hi> since the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> was his,
<note place="margin">No land like Canaans land.</note> how justly might the God of <hi>Heaven</hi> appoint this figurative Acknowledgement of a tenth to himself to be paid him out of this Land which so freely and miraculously he gave unto this people, whose case (in no civil respect hath parral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel with any people upon the face of the Earth? Yea and I affirm that whatever land shall pretend to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Pattern of Tithes, stands bound to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate (<hi>Heb.</hi> 7.) the Jewish Priests, the Sacrifices, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision, &amp;c. and to expect Christ Jesus yet to come for the abolishing of them &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fiftly,
<note place="margin">The Pope &amp; his Councells the chief pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters of Tiths among Christians.</note> What hath the servant of <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> to do with <hi>Belial, Anti Christ?</hi> For while we pretend the Name of <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> in the Matter, What <hi>Originall</hi> or warrant for the retaining of this <hi>Jewish</hi> Ceremony?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115335:5"/>Do we not find it to be a whorish Device of the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian</hi> Bishops, and a policie of that great <hi>Thief,</hi> and <hi>Robber</hi> of the World, the <hi>Pope,</hi> and of his <hi>Popish La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran</hi> Councels?</p>
            <p>Sixtly, hath not our most glorious <hi>Founder,</hi> the Lord <hi>Jesus</hi> (the only <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Master</hi> of all that truly follow him) expresly declared himself in those two famous Chapters touching his <hi>Ministrie Mat.</hi> 10. and <hi>Luke</hi> 10.
<note place="margin">The provision of the true Christ for his true Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors.</note> directing them without the least Mention of <hi>Tithes,</hi> and after their experience of his <hi>Provision,</hi> drawing this Confession out of their Mouths, that they lacked nothing? Great is the <hi>Noise,</hi> and great is the <hi>Controversie</hi> about the <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> their <hi>Maintenance,</hi> but doubtless were that <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in us which was in the twelve, and the seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we should not onely pretend to succeed them in ther <hi>Commissions,</hi> but we should also find their Success and meet <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> in the same experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>Seventhly,
<note place="margin">Tiths forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles.</note> When the Apostles the first <hi>Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> and <hi>Ambassadours</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> expresly han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled the matter of the <hi>Jewish Rites,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> (the holy <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God immediately</hi> and <hi>infallibly</hi> assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them) did they among some other particulars, which for a time they permitted, once make a title of Mention of this of <hi>Tithes? Acts</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Lastly, Is not the practice of the <hi>Lord Jesus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The practises of Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles as to maintenance.</note> and the practise of his Apostles, and of <hi>Paul</hi> especially (a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongst the <hi>Corinthians, Ephesians,</hi> and <hi>Thessalonians</hi>) <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>Presidents</hi> sufficient for servants of <hi>Christ Jesus?</hi> Tis true they received the volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and free <hi>Gift</hi> of such, whose Hearts God had made willing, but neither do we find that they depended upon others, nor that they bargained and capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115335:6"/>(above or under board) nor that they express<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and particularly <hi>demanded</hi> or <hi>desired</hi> a <hi>Gift (Phil.</hi> 4.)</p>
            <p>May not therefore that Man justly question whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever Christ Jesus sent him in such or such a way to preach that brings a spirit and a practice so different from Christ Jesus with him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Yea, but saith this Author, <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> saith (<hi>Luke</hi> v. 42.) ye tith <hi>Mint</hi> and <hi>Annise:</hi> These ought ye to have done, that is, Ye ought to pay Tithes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I answer, it is worth the Enquiry whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Tith of <hi>Mint</hi> and <hi>Rue,</hi> and every <hi>Garden Herb,</hi> was due by <hi>Moses Law,</hi> or was not a superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Pharisees,</hi> and consequently whether the <hi>Popish</hi> Tith (now extant) of Fish and Foul, and of all <hi>Personall Gaines,</hi> be not <hi>New yoakes,</hi> unto which the <hi>Jewes</hi> themselves were never subject:
<note place="margin">Greater Tiths then the Jews paid.</note> And conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> intended not that they ought to pay tithes of <hi>Mint</hi> and <hi>Rue,</hi> &amp;c. but that they ought to observe that <hi>Jewish</hi> Law of Tiths in general.</p>
            <p>Secondly, What if <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> told the <hi>Iews,</hi> that they ought to pay <hi>Tithes,</hi> they ought to be circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, to offer <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> what is this to the <hi>Christian Iews,</hi> the <hi>Christian Kingdome,</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> to whom <hi>Paul</hi> saith (<hi>Gal.</hi> 5.) If you be circumcised, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently, if you pay <hi>Tithes, Christ Iesus</hi> shall profit you nothing?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Where it was objected, we hear him not, why should we pay him? The Author of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons answereth: If thou live in a <hi>Parish</hi> where a <hi>Godly Minister</hi> is seated, it is thy sin to withdraw thy <hi>presence,</hi> but a greater to withdraw his Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>I reply and ask first if the Constitution of <hi>Parishes</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115335:6"/>be from the Institution, the <hi>Command,</hi> the <hi>Testament</hi> of <hi>Christ Iesus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Ministers sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify Servants, and what they ordinarily be in England.</note> Doth not the word <hi>Minister</hi> in plain English signifie a <hi>Servant</hi> or <hi>Waiter on the Parish?</hi> and then what <hi>Servants</hi> or <hi>Waiters</hi> shall we find those to be that scorne or shame to be called by their own Names in English, that will force their <hi>Ministrie</hi> or <hi>Service</hi> upon a Man in spight of him, that will serve him as they list themselves, that will be gone when they please and possibly can to more gainfull services, and whether they perform any Ministrie or Service or no, yet will force such wages from their Masters, as they never agreed to pay, yea although their Masters Children want <hi>Bread,</hi> and <hi>Cloathing,</hi> which is the case of thousands of poor <hi>Tith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payers</hi> in <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Be the <hi>Minister</hi> or <hi>Servant</hi> of the Parish never so godly, yet it is sin for that man to <hi>hear</hi> or <hi>maintain</hi> him, that cannot be fully perswaded in his heart, that his <hi>Ministry</hi> and <hi>Ministration</hi> is of <hi>God,</hi> and that he ought to maintain him, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>Lastly, Why should it be a greater sin for a man not to afford his <hi>Maintenance,</hi> than his presence? Not to pay <hi>Tithes,</hi> than not to join in the Word of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh,
<note place="margin">The great God of most Tith-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note> that I could not justly fear <hi>that the Belly</hi> is a greater <hi>God</hi> with most <hi>Tith-mongers Affections,</hi> (I dare maintain it with all <hi>Tith-mongers Practises</hi>) then is the true and living <hi>God,</hi> and his most holy and blessed Son <hi>Christ Jesus!</hi> Hence it is that in <hi>Holland,</hi> where (and in other <hi>Protestant</hi> Countries) <hi>Tithes</hi> are damned) I say, that the <hi>Dutch Clergy</hi> are so tame and gentle, for having their set <hi>wages</hi> from the <hi>State,</hi> not only may all <hi>Religions</hi> be in quiet amongst them, but also the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115335:7"/>part of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Nation, be of any or none, and of what <hi>Religion</hi> they please.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Further, whereas to a third Objection</hi> (to wit, he will not give us our due the Sacrament) <hi>it was answered, the Sacrament is not due but in Order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14 40. <hi>As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so that the Examination of Communicants, belongs not to the Minister, nor to the Minister with the Congregation, but to the Minister with the Ruling Elders, for which he quotes the singular book of the Vindication of</hi> Presbyterian <hi>Government. Secondly, he saith the Sacrament is not due to scandalous persons, Thieves and Robbers of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Grant the holy <hi>Decency,</hi> of all the instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> yea the necessity of <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> in all things,
<note place="margin">Masters won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of their Suppers by their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</note> that are not <hi>Babylonish</hi> and confused: yet what is this to the <hi>Popish</hi> and <hi>Prelaticall Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Trumpery,</hi> for which they pretended this Scripture? what warrant is this when a <hi>Minister</hi> our <hi>Servant</hi> of a <hi>Parish</hi> shall confess he is hired to performe the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry</hi> or <hi>Service</hi> of the <hi>Parish</hi> (amongst which Services that of administring the <hi>Supper,</hi> hath ever been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged one of the chief) when he shall take by force of armes his <hi>wages,</hi> and yet when his <hi>Masters</hi> come and expect their <hi>Supper,</hi> what warrant is there for this <hi>Servant,</hi> plainly to tell them, it is not <hi>Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> nor <hi>Order,</hi> that they eat any <hi>Supper</hi> at all? they may have <hi>Break-fast</hi> and <hi>Dinner, (Prayers</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and <hi>Psalms,</hi> and their children made Christian Souls) but they get no <hi>Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are not all these holy things joined together in the Ministry or Service of the Apostles?
<note place="margin">Politick su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition as to the Lords Supper.</note>
               <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. And may not he that pretends to be a <hi>Minister</hi> or Servant to a people, say he ought not to serve or Minister any of them, as well as not all of them? And indeed is it not a <hi>Relique</hi> still of the old <hi>Kneeling,</hi> yea, and this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115335:7"/>and that both <hi>Reliques</hi> of the old <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> to pretend so high a wall of <hi>Separation,</hi> between the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things of <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Baptism</hi> and <hi>Psalms,</hi> and <hi>Tiths,</hi> on this side the wall, and that one Service of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> on the other?</p>
            <p>It is worth the Examining (at another time) what is the Reason of that exceeding <hi>Noise</hi> and <hi>Do,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Politick My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries as to two points of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly The Lords Supper and Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> which the Popes and Prelates, and Presbyters of the world have made about those two <hi>Ordinances,</hi> the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and <hi>Excommunication:</hi> There is some Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in it. But at this time to the second Reason.</p>
            <p>The second Reason. <hi>Not paying of Tithes is a sin of a high Nature, it affronts and robs God</hi> Mal. 3. <hi>To rob a man in the high way, deserves death: To rob a King of his Plate and Jewells, deserves a</hi> Tormenting Death, <hi>but to rob the</hi> King of Glory, <hi>deserves the</hi> Fire <hi>of</hi> Hell.</p>
            <p>I answer, where did ever God appoint Death,
<note place="margin">Wonderfull strange justice</note> least of all a Tormenting Death, the penalty of taking away from common men or Kings this Worlds goods? And where hath <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> made such a <hi>Gradation</hi> as down from <hi>Death,</hi> and a <hi>Tormenting Death,</hi> to <hi>Hell Fire,</hi> for not paying of Tiths? Is not the <hi>English</hi> of this strange language this, the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath robb'd the King of greater matters than his <hi>Plate</hi> and <hi>Iewells,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deeply charg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuation, and vindicated.</note> therefore what tormenting Death should they suffer were the <hi>Rack</hi> and <hi>Fire</hi> in his keeping? yea and if the <hi>Parliament</hi> shall further dare to meddle with <hi>Tithes, Hell Fire</hi> and <hi>Damnation</hi> must be their portion; But he forgets what a man of blood, the late King was, and how the Blood of some thousands and 100 thousands cried after him, of <hi>French,</hi> of <hi>English, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish Protestants,</hi> yea and the <hi>Blood</hi> of his own <hi>Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi> Father <hi>Iames:</hi> as also he forgets that <hi>Christ Iesus</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115335:8"/>is come, and as a most glorious <hi>Sun</hi> hath dispelled those <hi>shadows,</hi> and that therefore to pay or receive <hi>Tithes</hi> in <hi>Gospel</hi> times is to rob <hi>God,</hi> to rob <hi>Christ,</hi> to rob <hi>Consciences,</hi> and <hi>Families,</hi> and whole <hi>Nations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Third Reason, <hi>Not paying of Tithes is a Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated sin, cheating added to stealing, for the Landlord bates the Tenant so much in his Rent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer,
<note place="margin">The charge of cheating re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</note> I never heard that ever <hi>Landlord</hi> in <hi>City</hi> or <hi>Country,</hi> bated a <hi>Farthing</hi> to his <hi>Tenant</hi> upon this account. This I have heard, that most <hi>Landlords</hi> in the <hi>City,</hi> have so scrued up, and stretcht (as wee say) upon the <hi>Rack</hi> and <hi>Tenters,</hi> their <hi>Rents</hi> to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry utmost, that the <hi>Backs</hi> of many Industrious and hopeful young men, are often quickly <hi>broken,</hi> and not able to discharge the very <hi>Landlords</hi> payment.</p>
            <p>And who is ignorant that in the <hi>Country</hi> (where <hi>Tiths</hi> fal heavy ordinarily upon the poor <hi>Husbandmen</hi>) that between these two <hi>Mill-stones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands two Mill-stones.</note> the <hi>Landlord</hi> and the <hi>Parson,</hi> many thou sand <hi>Families</hi> cry out of <hi>Oppre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssion,</hi> and some, that they are ground to Powder.</p>
            <p>The Fourth Reason, <hi>It is a sin, discouraging Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters in their work, contrary to</hi> Hezekiahs <hi>practise.</hi> 2 Chr. 31. <hi>He commanded the people that dwelt at</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>to give the Portion of the Priest and Levites, that they might be incouraged in the Law of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer, This is still the point in question: For although due <hi>Incouragements</hi> are to be given to <hi>Good,</hi> and due <hi>Discouragements</hi> to <hi>Evill:</hi> Yet every man is not bound by <hi>Purse</hi> and <hi>Person</hi> to encourage all the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands that say they are <hi>Gods Prophets</hi> and <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A two-fold square of our Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters.</note> &amp; <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> yea grant them to be true <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> even <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> themselves, yet no man is bound to incourage them beyond these two, their <hi>Consciences,</hi> &amp; their <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115335:8"/>both which <hi>Tithes</hi> do most violently force and usurpe upon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To the instance of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> we find not (as before) by the <hi>New Testament</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very land is <hi>Canaan,</hi> an <hi>holy land:</hi> that every <hi>City</hi> is <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> an holy <hi>City,</hi> that every Nation is <hi>Israel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Canaan and other Lands Compared.</note> an <hi>holy Nation,</hi> nor that there are the <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> extant, who have no <hi>Portion</hi> nor <hi>Inheritance</hi> in their respective Countries, as those <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> had not in their land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and were therfore other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise provided for out of the <hi>Lords</hi> own <hi>Allowance</hi> and Portion, and therefore he himself is called their <hi>Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> in which Ceremonial <hi>Type</hi> and <hi>Figure</hi> there seems to lie many spirituall and heveanly <hi>Misteries.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Christ Jesus the true King of the Jewes.</note>
               <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> the true <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> hath a <hi>Spiritual Kingdome</hi> in the <hi>Hearts,</hi> and <hi>Worships,</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> of all that truly desire to follow <hi>him,</hi> he it is that opens the door of their Hearts, and <hi>commands</hi> them by the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> not to spare their <hi>Bread</hi> nor <hi>Bloud</hi> from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of his <hi>Servants</hi> in his Christian work, &amp;c. And other <hi>Antitype</hi> of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> shall not the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilest <hi>Eagles</hi> eye find out amongst all the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of the world beside.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, who can but lament to see so many <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent</hi> Spirits lead <hi>slaves</hi> in the chains of <hi>Delusion?</hi> for were there not a wound in the eye, could it possibly be once heard amongst <hi>Christians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ministers of Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus turnd Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses Priests &amp; Levites for Tithes.</note> that <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> his <hi>Ministers</hi> should plead for the same way and <hi>Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> with the very <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Levites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Clergy</hi> of our times, will not be intituled <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Levites,</hi> no nor <hi>Priests</hi> &amp; <hi>Deacons,</hi> their late titles by Law, but <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> (and yet
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115335:9"/>not that in honest <hi>English</hi> neither) well if they be the Ministers of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Church,</hi> what have they to do with <hi>Moses</hi> and his carnal Sword and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies? Why must the <hi>Alarum</hi> be given, the <hi>Magist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> be wakened, and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> must cut and kill all that are not willing to pay the <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> their Tithes?</p>
            <p>Fiftly, what if King <hi>James,</hi> or King <hi>Charles,</hi> or any of the most sacred <hi>Hezekiahs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The turnings of Tithmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> and <hi>Annointeds</hi> of the Lord (as they have most <hi>Jewishly</hi> and <hi>Blasphemously</hi> bin called) what if, I say, they should with their <hi>sacred Swords,</hi> have commanded <hi>Circumcision</hi> to all the Males in their Dominions, the <hi>Passeover</hi> to be duely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, the <hi>Temple (Pauls</hi> or <hi>Westminster</hi>) re-edifyed, and dayly prayers to be made for the comming of the <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah</hi> in the flesh, and withall have but commanded incouragement to be given by Tithes to the <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Levites,</hi> how many thousands of such <hi>Tith-Merchants</hi> would have cried out, long live these blessed <hi>Hezekiahs Josiahs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> (as an Angel from Heaven) hath commanded Tithes to be paid for the Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> in the Law of the Lord, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And that I may not falsely so insinuate, let the Nations of <hi>Europe</hi> (but none more then this of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) testifie that the <hi>VVeather-Cock</hi> hath not more quickly turned with the Wind, then the <hi>Priests,</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> have turned and tackt about (with the <hi>Sword</hi>) to save the Incouragement of Tithes, and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>The fift Reason, <hi>By this sin the Defrauder robs his Soul of a Blessing, it being just with God to say to him, Thou withdrawest Maintenance from my Servant, and I will withdraw my Blessing from my own Oordinance,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115335:9"/>Thy Soul shall never prosper by any Sermon thou hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer First, if we poor Worms creep out of our Holes and talk of <hi>Justice</hi> with our <hi>Maker</hi> (as to the purest of our Services,) O, who can abide those devouring flames, &amp;c. So far am I from owning that blasphemous speech of one of the most blasphemous Kings in the World; King <hi>Iames,</hi> This Speech, he uttered in a most solemn Assembly in the <hi>Star-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi>
               <note place="margin">King James his blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note> and it was afterwards extolled in a Sermon at <hi>Pauls Cross,</hi> it was this, Whatever mine other sins are for which I ask God pardon, &amp;c. yet for doing of Justice I will not ask the Mercy of God. Gods Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice hath been dreadfull on him and his for their, <hi>Blasphemies</hi> even in this life, that all living may know God will not hold him guiltless that taketh his name in vain. Therefore.</p>
            <p>Secondly, May it not possibly be that we may thunder out Gods Judgements (as <hi>Solomons</hi> Madman) casting abroad <hi>Fire-brands, Arrowes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull abuse of the Name of God as to his Justice &amp; Judgements.</note> and <hi>Death</hi>) yea are not all the Sons of Men that ever heard of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> or <hi>Christ,</hi> apt to abuse both their Names and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staments for an end for an Interest; Do not all the many thousands and ten thousands <hi>Priests</hi> in the world, that pretend to worship one God by <hi>Moses,</hi> as the <hi>Iews,</hi> by <hi>Mahomet</hi> as the <hi>Turks,</hi> by <hi>Iesus</hi> as <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Protestants?</hi> do they not all pretend the thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt of Gods Justice &amp;c. But</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us examine what this Ordinance pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended is, It is called a Sermon:
<note place="margin">What a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is.</note> I ask what is that in <hi>English;</hi> the people wtll tell you that the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister</hi> goes up on high unto the <hi>Pulpit</hi> to bring Gods word down by an <hi>Hower-Glass;</hi> but some that know <hi>Latine</hi> will tell us that a <hi>Sermon</hi> is a <hi>Speech:</hi> And I ask
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115335:10"/>then why <hi>English</hi> men may not speak <hi>English</hi> and use the word <hi>Servant</hi> altogether for <hi>Minister,</hi> and the word <hi>Speech</hi> for <hi>Sermon:</hi> Doubtless it hath been half an <hi>Heresie</hi> to speak plain <hi>English,</hi> yea but to <hi>English</hi> that word <hi>Heresie</hi> it self, and words many which the Sun of <hi>Righteousness</hi> will more and more discover and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The very Truth is (although I fear to despise pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying, and to quench the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> by discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging any Prophet of God to read any parcel of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture (as Christ Jesus did <hi>Luke</hi> 4.)
<note place="margin">The mercies and blessings of English Sermons.</note> and to open and inlarge upon it more or less: Yea although I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the comparative Mercies of <hi>English Sermons,</hi> be yond the Old <hi>Paternosters,</hi> and <hi>Mumpsimus</hi> (as King <hi>Henry</hi> himself could call <hi>popish Devotions,</hi> &amp;c. yea and beyond our own, Our Fathers and our own <hi>Common-Prayers</hi> and <hi>Directories,</hi> which the <hi>Aegyptian Task-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> under <hi>Pharaoh</hi> (crying out of Idleness in going after Sermons) inslaved us with: Yea although I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the infinite Mercies of God, passing by what is not of himself, &amp;c. bringing much good out of Sermons to his people, ye and to many thousands souls as to personal conversion &amp;c. Yet</p>
            <p>I am humbly bold to affirm,
<note place="margin">Yet as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly used Images.</note> that not only your <hi>Popish</hi> and <hi>Superstitious, ignorant</hi> and <hi>drunken, railing</hi> and <hi>Treasonable Sermons</hi> or <hi>Speeches:</hi> but even your most refined, pend, painted and starched Speeches, as they are formally and Mercenarily practised, I say they are as very <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Pictures</hi> in Worship against the second Commandement, and against the Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Christ Jesus, as ever were, or are the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Images and Pictures, the Cross and Crucifix it self.</p>
            <p>Possibly, I may forget yea and will not enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115335:10"/>all the Charasters of such mysticall refined <hi>Images,</hi> yet one I must remember, which renders these speech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, like some Images, most terrible and dreadfull, and that is the high <hi>Insolency</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> of such Speeches, <hi>viz.</hi> the inforcing all Men (sometimes many more able to speak than the <hi>Speakers</hi>) to a deep silence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this <hi>Image,</hi> as if they learnt in the <hi>School</hi> of one <hi>Tyrannus</hi> (not so humane as that where <hi>Paul</hi> discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, but) where all must be received for Gospel, and no man dare to be so free, as but to make a <hi>Query</hi> or beg an Explanation.</p>
            <p>God knows I abhor that the least appearance of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civility</hi> should be offered to the very <hi>Jews,</hi> or <hi>Turks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full slavey of the English Nation to their Ministers or Servants.</note> or <hi>Indians,</hi> in the exercise of their <hi>Consciences</hi> and <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships;</hi> and I do profess it to be the duty of the <hi>Civill Magistrate</hi> wisely to <hi>prevent</hi> and <hi>remedy</hi> the Breach of the <hi>Civill peace.</hi> Yet can I not but ask what should be the Reason that our <hi>Translatours</hi> (either out of <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> or <hi>Subtilty</hi>) should so abuse us, as to turn that place <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. Paul <hi>preached unto them,</hi> when they sure can tell, the true word is <hi>Paul Discoursed, discours<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> as in a <hi>Dialogue</hi> or Conference, and that verse 9. <hi>while</hi> Paul <hi>was long</hi> Preaching, the same word is <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursing</hi> or <hi>conferring:</hi> which implies, that the <hi>Schoole</hi> of Christ is for <hi>Instruction,</hi> which ever presupposeth <hi>Ignorance, Doubts, Objections, Inquisitions,</hi> for which there is no room, when so great a <hi>Master</hi> shall speak <hi>Oracles,</hi> and One alone (as the Priest serves the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the <hi>Wine</hi> in the <hi>Mass.</hi>) shall drink up all the <hi>Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Paper which now I answer, clamours out (like <hi>Solomons strange</hi> Woman) <hi>Theeves, Cheators, Robbers: Sacrilegious</hi> Curses upon their <hi>Bodies,</hi> Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses upon their Estates, Curses upon their Souls in <hi>Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115335:11"/>for not paying of <hi>Tithes!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Four Presum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting a Thief and Rebber.</note> I would not use Recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, nor retort: Yet I shall pray this <hi>Author</hi> and all men to consider, whether amongst other <hi>presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and grounds of suspicion, these four do not look like shrewd ones of at least some (worthily to be) su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected persons.</p>
            <p>First,
<note place="margin">First, not ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own name.</note> When persons endure not to hear of their own name in English, The <hi>Bishop</hi> endur'd not to be cal'd <hi>Over-seer,</hi> nor the <hi>Minister</hi> by the name <hi>Servant:</hi> and instead of the, Minister of the Parish, the Servant of the Parish, our Minister, our Servant; How would this plain English be despised? (and doubtless if the name, the thing much more)? would it be born with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to say instead of a <hi>Sermon preached,</hi> a <hi>speech made?</hi> would not its own name seem too base for it self, in true and honest English? and yet the most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Judges and Councellors, and Parliament worthies are not ashamed to own that word [a <hi>Speech</hi>] in English.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Is is <hi>suspicious,</hi> when a man shall not be content in the Town or place where he lives, with a moderate proportion of Condition,
<note place="margin">Secondly, when discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with a low condition he prays upon his Neighbors.</note> but (although he have of his own) he will force out of his Neighbors labours, and sometimes poverties, an higher and an unequall portion.</p>
            <p>For (according to the computation of that indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious Author of the <hi>Tith-gatherers, no Gospell gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:</hi>) if this Nation were divided, into 500. shares, the Clergy, which are but one to 500, will challenge to themselves (all things computed) 20. shares of 500 for their portion.</p>
            <p>Yet more plainly, in a Country Town (for indeed the Burthen seems to lie heaviest upon poor <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:</hi>) suppose 500 Men and Women in a Country Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115335:11"/>and all the Land in that parish amount to 2000l. <hi>per annum,</hi> the Parson (all things computed) claims about 400l. (one fifth) for his share, and leaves all the rest 499. persons to be content with about 3 l. 4s. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Impatiencie of Pauls La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to Pauls Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strie, suspici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> when a man shall not endure to hear of any other course of life and maintenance, yea although he be not the Son of a <hi>Noble,</hi> but the off-spring of a shrub, yet if he be once cowl'd with the Title of a Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, a Priest, a Preacher, a Minister, Oh, how dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graceful it is to put hand to a Spade, &amp;c? Now, no Seat but the Highest Seat in the Synagogue, no room, but the Uppermost room at Feasts, and the Salutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Rabbi, Doctor,</hi> &amp;c. in the market place, if Christ Jesus and all experience say true.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is very suspicious, when a man cannot patiently endure to be questioned, examined, or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed in his affirmations: when if (some) men had their wills, it should be as deadly a sin, and as dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to question the least of their <hi>Doctrines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Impatiencie of Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion sheweth Presumption of Falshood.</note> as it is in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries, to question the <hi>Popes Canons,</hi> or the <hi>Turkes Alcoran.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not unusuall with all that would be the onely <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Masters</hi> of Religion in the World to urge <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. Let him that is taught in the <hi>Word</hi> communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to him that teacheth in all good things. But, what shall we think of those teachers that endure not a question to be proposed in their <hi>Schools,</hi> Teaching-places, neither by <hi>Strangers,</hi> nor their <hi>Schollars,</hi> and that of all <hi>Schollars,</hi> dislike those most who are most searching and inquisitive?</p>
            <p>If such <hi>Teachers</hi> can be honest in the <hi>Schooles</hi> of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> and <hi>Civill</hi> learning, yet I am sure he is not like <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> nor his Servant <hi>Paul,</hi> who practised and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115335:12"/>commanded his Servants in meekness to instruct even those that oppose themselves (what though <hi>Jew,</hi> or <hi>Turk,</hi> or <hi>Papist,</hi> or <hi>Pagan</hi>) by the word of Truth and Meekness convincing <hi>Gainsayers</hi>) instructing the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posites and waiting whether God will give them <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know the <hi>Outcries</hi> are made of despising the Word of God, of despising Preaching, despising Learning, destroying of souls &amp;c. and though possibly I might answer many other waies, yet what should a <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> say, but desire to be a Fool for <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> sake, and to desire to know nothing but <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> and him nailed to the <hi>Gallowes,</hi> and I will end this pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage with a two fold <hi>observation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, It is lamentably found true, that within these twelve years last past, many, many almost all of those called <hi>Preachers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ministers of England withered.</note> excellent for <hi>parts,</hi> for <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation,</hi> for <hi>Piety,</hi> for <hi>Knowledge,</hi> for <hi>utterance</hi> and much <hi>good</hi> wrought by them; have upon the discoveries from <hi>Christ</hi> of the <hi>Liberties</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> laboured to suppress them, and loved their <hi>Honors,</hi> their <hi>Tithes,</hi> more than God, tis lamentable I say to observe how almost all have not only lost their <hi>Honors,</hi> their most conscionable <hi>Auditors,</hi> but their <hi>Parts</hi> and and <hi>Abilities,</hi> are even withered and dry, and are no more like unto themselves, than <hi>Sampson</hi> was like <hi>Sampson</hi> when he was <hi>unsampsoned</hi> by <hi>Delilah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Knowledge more than ever increased in <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> Since the People of this Nation, and the People of <hi>God</hi> in it have for these twelve years past been more inlightned, in the mysterie of their slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Liberties, both in <hi>Army,</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> and that people have dared to speak and confer, and to examine what <hi>Paul</hi> himself delivers (as the <hi>Bereans</hi> did) the People of this Nation have more increased in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115335:12"/>the <hi>Experimentall</hi> knowledge of the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> than in many twenties and hundreds of years before, while under the <hi>Popish</hi> or <hi>Protestant</hi> Bondage and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.</p>
            <p>The sixth Reason. <hi>This not paying of Tithes, brings Gods Curse upon the estate</hi> Mal. 3. <hi>You are cursed with a Curse &amp;c. they grudge the Minister his Maintenance, and God grudgeth them even bread for their Families; so that usually they turn Banckrupts, or fall into Debt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer. There be two parts of this Reason: The first the Matter of <hi>Doctrine</hi> concerning <hi>Tithes</hi> supposed to be Gods Ordinance, in <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> his Kingdome (but of the inconsistency of <hi>Tithes</hi> with true <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,</hi> enough before)</p>
            <p>The second is matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> and the experience how God hath cursed such as have not paid <hi>Tithes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Unto which I answer, First, some to the praise of Gods mercy profess,
<note place="margin">Gods blessing on some who pay nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Tithes.</note> that since they have (out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science to God, and not out of Covetuousness or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness) hazarded their Names and estates in not pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Tithes,</hi> God hath not only graciously imbraced them with his <hi>Right hand</hi> of Soul refreshings in his dear Son, but also hath sustained their Heads, with a merciful <hi>Left hand</hi> of outward Blessings upon their Callings and Labours, and that in some gracious mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure more than formerly.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Be it otherwise (it may be) with many who have refused to pay or to receive Tithes: yet what soul hath in uprightness parted with a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for God, and hath not received his hundred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, and whose <hi>Dry Morsell</hi> and <hi>Dinner</hi> of Green hearbs, is not fatter and sweeter then an house full of Sacrifices of strife, with God, and with his own Spirit and Conscience?</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115335:13"/>
            <p>Thirdly, is there a poor Citizen or Countrey-man wounded in his estate and Trading, lively-hood and Maintenance? I more then fear I may ask thefe 2 Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions.</p>
            <p>First, Is not the Author of these Questions two neer a kin, to that <hi>Priest</hi> and that <hi>Levite,</hi> who both went on the other side? He is broke, he is in debt, there let him lie, let some vile <hi>Samaritan,</hi> or who will look after him: Nay tis a just vengeance of God upon him, tis just he should fall amongst <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers</hi> who robs God and his holy <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> of their Tithes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ask whether it be not (sometimes) a shrewd suspition,
<note place="margin">The Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordshire and of the Nation to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> that such men as pass by wounded men on the other side, calling them <hi>Banckrupts,</hi> &amp;c. have had some hand or finger in the very wounding of them? And indeed if the <hi>Husbandmen</hi> of <hi>Hartford</hi>-shire, and of other shires that have petitioned the High Court of Parliament, (and if all such woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Husbandmen in all <hi>England</hi>) say true; This very Tith, this robbing them of the tenth and more of their estate and labours, hath made many thousands and ten thousands, some run in debts, some turn <hi>Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts,</hi> some want <hi>Bread</hi> to their Families, and sigh and groane, and cry to God and the State for suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour.</p>
            <p>The seventh Reason. <hi>It is a sin against the Gospell, this puts out the light by taking away the oil that feeds it, like</hi> Julian <hi>(as is observed in the excellent Vindication of</hi> Presbyterian <hi>Government) who while other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours by Persecution took away the</hi> Ministers, <hi>he by taking away</hi> Tithes <hi>took away the</hi> Ministery <hi>it self.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer, It is a grand Mistake, and like the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115335:13"/>Beast in the <hi>Revel.</hi> full of the names of <hi>Blasphemie,</hi> that makes a <hi>Jewish</hi> and <hi>Popish Ceremony</hi> the very <hi>Oil</hi> that feeds the light of the Gospel.</p>
            <p>First, it highly blasphemes or speaks evil of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit of God, by whom alone all the <hi>Ministrations,</hi> and <hi>Operations</hi> of Christ Jesus are effected,
<note place="margin">The Golden Oil in Zach. not Tiths.</note> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom no man can say (truely) that <hi>Iesus</hi> is the <hi>Christ,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 12. And <hi>Zach.</hi> 6. wherein we read of the Golden <hi>Candlestick,</hi> and the seven Golden <hi>Lamps</hi> thereof, and the two <hi>Olive Trees,</hi> and two <hi>Olive Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;</hi> the Question is, What be these? And the Answer is vers. 6. Not by Might, nor by Power, but by my Spirit, saith the <hi>Lord:</hi> I ask here (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing that I deny not the due use of Gods meanes yet) whether in the building both of the <hi>Materiall,</hi> and <hi>Spirituall Temple,</hi> whether in the feeding of the <hi>Materiall Lamp,</hi> and <hi>Light,</hi> or the <hi>Spirituall,</hi> the most holy <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> be not that Oil, and not <hi>Tiths</hi> and <hi>Monies,</hi> by which the holy light and work of God is propagated?</p>
            <p>There were two famous <hi>Oils</hi> commanded of the <hi>Lord</hi> to <hi>Moses.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Famous oils in the Law, yet neither typing out Tiths.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The first, that of <hi>Oile Olive</hi> beaten for the daily sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of the <hi>Lamp, Exod.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>The second, that compounded of many <hi>Spices,</hi> for the <hi>Annointing</hi> and <hi>Sanctifying</hi> of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> the <hi>Priest,</hi> the <hi>Vessells,</hi> &amp;c, and whosoever made the like to this Oile, he was to be cut off from his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>First, If the first of these did signifie the Word of God, as some conceive, yet doubtless the second must clearly signifie the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> who sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and operates all in all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If one should signifie the Word which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115335:14"/>the first <hi>Christians</hi> were daily in, without Tiths or set Maintenance, yet the gracious concomitance and presence of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God is promised with the <hi>Word</hi> of God to <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> the <hi>Annointed</hi> and to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> his <hi>Annointed</hi> ones, <hi>Isa.</hi> 59. My VVord and my Spirit in thy Mouth,
<note place="margin">The Spirit &amp; Word of God expresly ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified.</note> and the Mouth of thy Seed and the Mouth of thy <hi>Seeds Seed</hi> from henceforth and for ever.</p>
            <p>May we not say to that soul thy Money perish with thee, who counterfeits this <hi>Holy Oil,</hi> this most holy and most free <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, and (after the <hi>Bishops</hi> cry No <hi>Bishop, no King</hi> &amp;c.) fill the world with clamours, <hi>No Tiths, no Gospell?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, This Doctrine blasphemes <hi>Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Founder</hi> of <hi>Christians,</hi> who (if <hi>Tither</hi> be such a <hi>Fundamental,</hi> and no <hi>Tithes,</hi> no <hi>Ministry</hi>) so infinitly forgot himself, as to leave out <hi>Tithes</hi> out of his last <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Testament:
<note place="margin">Fowle asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on Christ Jesus.</note> Moses</hi> was not so unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, for in his Testament they were not forgotten, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But Oh, the patience and the meekness of the lamb of God, who hath the seven Horns, and the seven Eyes, (signifying the holy Spirit of God, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.) wherein are fulness of Power, Wisdom, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, most gloriously sufficient to mannage his <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Works</hi> and <hi>Wars</hi> without consulting with <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Priests</hi> about Money (none of the <hi>sinews</hi> of his holy <hi>War</hi>) about <hi>Taxes,</hi> and <hi>Tiths,</hi> which people must pay to be converted, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Oh, the patience of the Son of <hi>God</hi> thus to endure the <hi>Contradictions</hi> and <hi>Lyes</hi> of sinners, for let but an impartial <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>Humility, Love, self-denial,</hi> and <hi>Content</hi> (Gods Spirit the President) examine the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and it shall be found as clear as the Sun. That</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115335:14"/>
            <p>First,
<note place="margin">Christ's care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</note>
               <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> appointed no other <hi>Maintenance</hi> to any of his <hi>Ministe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> (either <hi>Apostolical</hi> or <hi>Pastoral,</hi> but such as were (I would not call them <hi>Eleemosynary</hi> with <hi>Wickeliffe</hi>) but truly and simply <hi>Free</hi> and <hi>Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That the <hi>Lord Jesus</hi> hath discovered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable <hi>Wisdome</hi> in his <hi>care,</hi> For such <hi>Maintenance</hi> and none else can possibly suit the <hi>Ends</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus;</hi> No nor the <hi>Spirits</hi> and <hi>Supplies</hi> of such as truly Minister or wait on him or his.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, How can it be said No [<hi>Tith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The first Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers of Christ Jesus most glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous without the thought of Tithes.</note> No <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry,</hi>] when that holy Scripture, and all the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of true <hi>Christianity</hi> in the world can tell us how <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> rode forth (<hi>Revel.</hi> 6.) upon his <hi>White Horse</hi> or <hi>Horses,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> of Truth and Meekness, spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally subduing and saving the souls of millions, when we hear not a Title of the sound of <hi>Tithes, Rom.</hi> 10. and through the Acts of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and <hi>Epistles</hi> to the <hi>Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, See how the doctrine <hi>[No Tithes, No Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry]</hi> blasphemes and destroyes the whole Profession and <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>Christianity</hi> out of the world. For if those holy Conclusions be true, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. How can men call upon <hi>God</hi> in whom they believe not? How can they <hi>believe</hi> without <hi>hearing?</hi> how can they <hi>hear</hi> without a <hi>Preacher?</hi> How can they <hi>preach</hi> except they be <hi>sent?</hi> Why then, if no <hi>Tithes,</hi> no <hi>Ministry,</hi> no <hi>Preaching,</hi> no <hi>Hearing,</hi> no <hi>Beleeving,</hi> and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no <hi>calling</hi> upon or <hi>Worshipping</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus</hi> in the world.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Grant (without dispute) those practises of <hi>Julian,</hi> both as <hi>Lion</hi> and a <hi>Fox,</hi> be true, and that he was resolved to expel his enemy the <hi>Galilean (Christ Jesus)</hi> out of the world: Grant that by taking away
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115335:15"/>
               <hi>Tithes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Julians policy by taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Tithes, to take away the Ministry exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</note> he intended to take away the <hi>Ministry:</hi> Yet doth not the <hi>Foolishness</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> befool the <hi>Wisdome</hi> of this <hi>Julian,</hi> and of all such politick heads <hi>(like Julians)</hi> who dream that outward <hi>Maintenance</hi> or the <hi>want</hi> of it, can uphold or overthrow the <hi>Ministry</hi> or <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>Christs</hi> messengers?</p>
            <p>Did it ever so in <hi>Christs</hi> own <hi>time, person</hi> or <hi>practise?</hi> Did it so in any of the <hi>Evangelists</hi> writings or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords? Did it so in the tenth of <hi>Mat.</hi> or tenth of <hi>Luke?</hi> Did it so in all the first Saints, <hi>Apostles,</hi> or <hi>Churches,</hi> that we read of, in either the <hi>Acts,</hi> or <hi>Epistles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, is not that <hi>Light,</hi> which is contrary unto this <hi>dark</hi> position? Did not the <hi>Christian Profession,</hi> more suffer and lose from the <hi>Revenues</hi> and <hi>Honours</hi> with which <hi>Constantine</hi> is said to <hi>exalt</hi> (and throw down) the <hi>Ministers</hi> and <hi>Bishops</hi> of his time?
<note place="margin">Christianity lost more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, than Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian or Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And is it not contrary to other Gardens, that the Garden of Christ Jesus, hath ever been known to grow and flourish more in the Autum and Winter of Lowness, wants, and persecutions, Than in the Spring and Summer of Riches, Peace. Authority, &amp;c? But</p>
            <p>Lastly, I adore the depths of the wisdome of God, who (fearful in praises) forceth his praise by confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, out of the mouths of us poor sinners: For doth not this Author plainly tell the world, what is in the very Heart of this <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Book (which this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor so extolleth) and in the very heart of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government,
<note place="margin">The heart and soul of the Presbyterian Ministry.</note> which that book maintaineth? <hi>No Tithes, no Ministry,</hi> is the Heart and soul of it, the rest is but <hi>Flesh</hi> and Blood, skin and Bones, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs, Outworks, &amp;c. No, the Business is (as the Priest used to say, the Soul leaps not forth of <hi>Purgatory</hi> untill the Money just chink in the <hi>Bason</hi>) No <hi>Peny,</hi> no <hi>Paternoster,</hi> no <hi>Tithes,</hi> no <hi>Teaching,</hi> no <hi>pay,</hi> no <hi>pray,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115335:15"/>no <hi>Feasting,</hi> no <hi>Fasting,</hi> no <hi>Gaine,</hi> no <hi>Godliness,</hi> nor <hi>God,</hi> nor <hi>Christ,</hi> nor <hi>Heaven, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I end this seventh Reason with this <hi>Appeal</hi> to all Men and ask, whether it be not the Constant <hi>Character</hi> of suspicion in all <hi>Affairs</hi> and <hi>Agents</hi> in the World, when it proves a <hi>Money Matter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Money Matter.</note> especially in such <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents</hi> or <hi>Officers,</hi> who (pretend at least and) say their <hi>Master</hi> the <hi>Lord Jesus</hi> hath freely given them his <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Spirituall Gifts,</hi> hath promised freely and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly to provide for them, and to reward and crown then?</p>
            <p>And is not this apparent to all the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An Appeale to the people of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to the present pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in it.</note> that (notwithstanding these <hi>Boasts</hi> of the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Books,</hi> and Government yet) the practises of such as open Gods word throughout the Nation without <hi>Tithes,</hi> and of such as go higher, and open it without <hi>Stipend</hi> or <hi>Reward,</hi> other than proceeds from the love of their hearers, I say that the <hi>Practises</hi> of such come neerer to true ingenuous <hi>Honesty</hi> and true sincere Christianity?</p>
            <p>The eighth Reason. <hi>It is a sin that will not be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned upon Repentance, unless there be a restitution as well as repentance, according to that Speech of</hi> Austin, Non remittitur peccatum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer, This Reason is founded upon a treble Quicksand falsely supposing</p>
            <p>First, that not paying of Tithes is <hi>stealing, cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Robbing,</hi> the contrary whereof I have proved, and it will in times approaching be so clear by the shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Sun of <hi>Righteousness</hi> that proof will not be needed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That a Sinne may be repented of (he means truely repented of, or he saith nothing) and yet not pardoned: contrary to the nature of <hi>Gods
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115335:16"/>Mrcy,</hi> to the Nature of his <hi>promises,</hi> to the <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> and to the true peace and comfort of all poor wounded Sinners.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">True Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution are Companions.</note> That a sin of <hi>Cheating, Theft, Robbery,</hi> &amp;c. may be repented of without Restitution: The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary whereof is true either by Restitution in Kind, or Value, or Desire, in the want of <hi>Ability:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I boldly affirm that all such <hi>Church Thieves</hi> who (with <hi>Iosephs Mistris</hi> cry <hi>Whore</hi> first, and yet) have rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the <hi>Gospell,</hi> rob'd poor <hi>Families,</hi> and rob'd the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> by this <hi>Popish</hi> and <hi>Iewish</hi> three toothed Hook of Tithing: I say, such Theives cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press true Repentance without the abovesaid Restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The ninth Reason is. <hi>This sin will cry for vengeance when the Sinner is on his Death bed crying for mercy</hi> Jam. 5.3. <hi>and the Author concludes: If the Hire of Labourers in Mens Ʋineyards kept back by fraud cryeth, how dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full will the cry be of the Hire of Gods Labourers in Gods Ʋineyard kept back by Robbers and Defrauders? I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to think of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer, this is no New Vizard whereby <hi>Popish Tith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers</hi> and <hi>Tith Merchants</hi> (<hi>Revel.</hi> 18.) have frighted thousands and ten thousands, and Millions of Treasure from the purses of our Forefathers! what, rob the <hi>Priest?</hi> rob God? Hell Fire, purgatorie, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As I do profess it to be unchristian to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Cup of cold water from any hand without a gratefull mind and Retribution to our power: so, much less spiritual waters of life &amp;c. Yea further where compacts are made and an Hire promised, either in <hi>Corporall</hi> or <hi>Spirituall Whoredome,</hi> there is a kind of justice in due payment. But what shall we say to such <hi>Reapers</hi> of our Fields (for the Author mistakes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115335:16"/>
               <hi>Ʋineyards</hi> for <hi>Fields,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Strange spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Reapers.</note>
               <hi>Wine</hi> for <hi>Bread</hi>) as will force themselves into all the <hi>Fields</hi> of a Town as will work how they please and not cut down as other <hi>Reapers,</hi> do for their Hire? as keep out all other <hi>Reapers</hi> by force, and not suffer the Owner to hire such <hi>Reapers</hi> as he is better perswaded of: as will leave their work and forsake the <hi>Field</hi> on a suddain, &amp; be an hundred mile off in other Fields for greater hire and wages! Who, although the <hi>Husbandmen</hi> see it for their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to make use of other help, yet these <hi>Reapers</hi> (these <hi>Robbers</hi>) will be paid, or else by fire and sword they will have it out of the very Throats and Bowels of the poor <hi>Husbandmen</hi> and their Children?
<note place="margin">Conclusion.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I fear the high <hi>Clamour</hi> of these nine Reasons have rendred this Answer lowder than. I desire to give to men professing the name and fear of God: I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the (not inconsiderable) pleas of <hi>Impropriatours:</hi> and the many, not to be neglected, Arguments of many 1000 and many 10000 (for maintenance) who in this and other Countries pretend to be the <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Christ Iesus:</hi> And we know the late and Christian care of the <hi>Lord Generall</hi> and the <hi>Officers</hi> of the Army, praying the Parliaments care as to Tiths and the pleas belonging: It behooves us to beg of God, the Spirit of Understanding and Wisdome and the fear of <hi>Iehovah</hi> upon that <hi>High Assembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet however the Parliament shall please to deal with Impropriations, however with the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Priests</hi> who endeavoured to blow up King <hi>Iames</hi> his Parliament, however with <hi>Presbyterian Priests</hi> who have so oft endeavoured to blow up this. Yet I am humbly confident to maintain.</p>
            <p>First, that Tiths have been a yoak which neither we nor our Fathers have been able to bear, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115335:17"/>
            <p>Secondly, Freedome is the peoples right and cry.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Who ever enters into Christs work any other way than by Christ the doors appointment, he is a Thief and a Robber.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If this most honourable Parliament, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and Army hold their peace, the God of Heaven will raise up other stones to cry and to deliver this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his People in it from these yoaks.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, Christ Jesus the Sun of Glory and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness hath lighted up such a Candle in the midst of this Nation, and from hence in the midst of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the world (as to Soul-freedom) that all the Devils of Hell shall never be able to extinquish.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Christs witnesses, until the time appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, must resolve to give an humble and yet couragious witness, even to bonds and death, against this Tith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Idol. And</p>
            <p>Lastly, Whoever he be that payeth or receiveth Tiths [whatever his person be otherwise to God yet] in this practise, he with the <hi>Iewes</hi> denies Christ Jesus yet to be come, and is no Christian but a Jew.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>The <hi>Husbandmans Plea against Tithes,</hi> and <hi>Tith-Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers no Gospell Gatherers,</hi> are sold at <hi>William Lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nars</hi> at the <hi>Black-moor</hi> neer <hi>Fleet-bridge.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>